Guide to the Danford Barney Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Danford Barney papers
1877-1953
YCAL MSS 466
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.13
(9 boxes)
The Danford Barney papers contains correspondence, drafts of writings, photographs, and other material relating to poet and photographer Danford Barney. Correspondence in the collection contains letters from many Yale-affiliated faculty, authors, and collaborators, including Stephen Vincent Benét, William Rose Benét, Henry Seidel Canby, John Farrar, Brian Hooker, Benjamin R. C. Low, William Lyon Phelps, and Thornton Wilder, as well as authors who commented on Barney's work, such as John Hall Wheelock, and authors whose work interested him, such as A. E. Housman and E. A. Robinson. Writings contains drafts and fragments for several manuscripts, including the original autograph drafts, corrected, of the early poems published as Dust of Stars (1916), as well as typescript fair copies of later, unpublished collections of poems, "Silly Sagas of the Sea" and "Songs of Sorts." Other materials include photographic prints by Barney, identification papers, biographical and genealogical information, and clippings and printed ephemera.
Barney, Danford, 1892-1952
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Danford Barney, 1953, and bequest of Francis Hyde Bangs, 1964.
Custodial History
The photographs by Danford Barney housed in Oversize storage (boxes 4-8) were acquired by the library at the bequest of Francis Hyde Bangs in 1964. Following Barney's death in 1952, Dorothy Barney married long-time friend Francis Hyde Bangs. They remained married until her death in 1961. The photographs, presumably in their custody since 1952, were donated to the library along with Bangs's personal papers following his death.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 9 (nitrate negatives): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Associated Materials
Additional photographic prints by Danford Barney can be found in the Bangs Family Papers (YCAL MSS 47).
Danford Barney (1892-1952)
In the 1920s Danford Barney was associated with a group of young Yale poets that included Stephen Vincent Benét, Archibald MacLeish, Phelps Putnam, and John Farrar. Early in the decade, Barney published a literary magazine, Parabalou, containing original poems by members of the group. Between 1916, when he graduated from Yale, and 1945, he published six volumes of his own poetry, including Dust of Stars (1916), Chords of Albireo (1920), In the Comet's Hair (1921), Sardonyx (1926), Selected Poems Old and New (1942), and Songs Not for Brides (1945).
In the First World War, Barney served with the Yale Mobile Hospital Unit, which was attached to American armies in the battles of Saint-Mihiel and Meuse-Argonne. From 1922 until 1930 Barney maintained a photographic studio in New York, where he made a series of portraits of authors and artists. He was twice married, first to Gertrude Wells, with whom he had three daughters, and later to Dorothy Bartlett.
Biographical information on Danford Barney taken from "DANFORD BARNEY JR., I CONNECTICUT POET, 59I." New York Times (1923-Current file) 22 May 1952, ProQuest Historical Newspapers The New York Times (1851-2007), ProQuest. Web. (accessed 18 May 2011). Additional biographical information on Barney can be found in the essay by Francis Hyde Bang, "Danford Barney: Poet," The Yale University Library Gazette 27, 4 (April 1953): 131-148.
Scope and Contents
The Danford Barney papers contains correspondence, drafts of writings, photographs, and other material relating to poet and photographer Danford Barney. Correspondence in the collection contains letters from many Yale-affiliated faculty, authors, and collaborators, including Stephen Vincent Benét, William Rose Benét, Henry Seidel Canby, John Farrar, Brian Hooker, Benjamin R. C. Low, William Lyon Phelps, and Thornton Wilder, as well as authors who commented on Barney's work, such as John Hall Wheelock, and authors whose work interested him, such as A. E. Housman and E. A. Robinson. Writings contains drafts and fragments for several manuscripts, including the original autograph drafts, corrected, of the early poems published as Dust of Stars (1916), as well as fair typescript copies of later, unpublished collections of poems, "Silly Sagas of the Sea" and "Songs of Sorts." Other materials include photographic prints by Barney, identification papers, biographical and genealogical information, and clippings and printed ephemera.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1877-1952. II. Writings, 1916-1953. III. Photographs, undated. IV. Other Material, 1896-1950.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Photographers; Poets; Barney, Danford, 1892-1952; Benét, Stephen Vincent, 1898-1943; Benét, William Rose, 1886-1950; Canby, Henry Seidel, 1878-1961; Hooker, Brian, 1880-1946; Housman, A. E. (Alfred Edward), 1859-1936; Low, Benjamin Robbins Curtis, 1880-1941; Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943; Robinson, Edwin Arlington, 1869-1935; Wheelock, John Hall, 1886-1978; Wilder, Thornton, 1897-1975
- Correspondence, 1877-1952; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by last name.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Correspondence consists chiefly of letters to Danford Barney from others. Correspondents include many Yale-affiliated faculty, authors, and collaborators, including Stephen Vincent Benét, his brother William Rose Benét, Henry Seidel Canby, John Farrar, Brian Hooker, Benjamin R. C. Low, William Lyons Phelps, and Thornton Wilder, as well as authors who either commented on Barney's work, such as John Hall Wheelock, or whose work interested him, such as A. E. Housman and E. A. Robinson.
  - List of letters addressed to Danford Barney, undated (Box 1)
  - Adams, H. S., 1923 February 21 (Box 1)
  - Angell, James R., 1924 May 15 (Box 1)
  - Bates, Katharine Lee, 1925 July 11 (Box 1)
  - Benét, Stephen Vincent, [1920 September 13] (Box 1)
  - Benét, William Rose, 1916, 1925 (Box 1)
  - Blashfield, Edwin Howland, 1923 April 19 (Box 1)
  - Brush, George de Forest, 1923 July 1 (Box 1)
  - Bynner, Witter, 1942 October 29 (Box 1)
  - Canby, Henry Seidel, 1924-1925 (Box 1)
  - Chase, Joseph Cummings, 1942 May 27 (Box 1)
  - Cortissoz, Royal, 1923 April (Box 1)
  - Dodd, Lee Wilson, 1923 May 1 (Box 1)
  - Drinkwater, John, 1925 July 25 (Box 1)
  - Farrar, John, 1925 July 13 (Box 1)
  - Frost, Robert, 1925 July 27 (Box 1)
  - Garland, Hamlin, 1924 (Box 1)
  - George H. Doran Company, 1923 December 12 (Box 1)
  - Greenslet, Ferris, 1923 August 28 (Box 1)
    Third-party letter to John Hall Wheelock
  - Hardy, Florence Emily, 1925 July 30 (Box 1)
  - Hillyer, Robert, [19]25 July 13 (Box 1)
  - Hooker, Brian, 1919, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Housman, A. E., 1925 July 21 (Box 1)
  - Kilmer, Joyce, 1917 June 6 (Box 1)
  - Kirby, Rollin, [19]41 January 17 (Box 1)
  - Low, Benjamin Robbins Curtis, 1916 May 11 (Box 1)
  - "M" general, 1919, 1922 (Box 1)
  - Martin, Edward S., 1923 September 26 (Box 1)
  - Masefield, John, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Morton, David, 1925 June 17 (Box 1)
  - Mountbatten of Burman, Edwina Ashley Mountbatten, [19]22 November 27 (Box 1)
  - Percy, William Alexander, undated (Box 1)
  - Phelps, William Lyon, 1942 November 26 (Box 1)
  - Robinson, E. A. (Edwin Arlington), 1925 July 29 (Box 1)
  - Steele, Frederic Dorr, 1942 April 1 (Box 1)
  - Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1914 March 21 (Box 1)
  - Teasdale, Sara, 1925 July 29 (Box 1)
  - [Tilton], Freeman, 1945, undated (Box 1)
  - Vogue Company, 1922 November 25 (Box 1)
  - Wagstaff, Blanche Shoemaker, 1914-1916, undated (Box 1)
  - Wheelock, John Hall, 1914-1945 (Box 1)
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1928, undated (Box 1)
  - Williams, Jesse Lynch, 1923 March 27 (Box 1)
  - Yale Alumni Weekly, 1913 July 29 (Box 1)
  - Young, Art, n.y. January 13 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, 1925 August 8 (Box 1)
  - Unsorted correspondence, 1877-1952, undated; 2 (Box 1)
- Writings, 1916-1953; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Series II. Writings contains drafts and fragments for several manuscripts and features the original autograph drafts, most corrected, of the early poems published as Dust of Stars (1916) and fair typescript drafts for what appear to be later, unpublished compilations of poems, "Silly Sagas of the Sea" and "Songs of Sorts."
  - Dust of Stars, drafts, 1916, undated (Box 1)
  - "A Minor Operation," draft, undated (Box 1)
  - "Neo Platonism," notebook, 1920, undated (Box 1)
  - "Round Robin", 1932 (Box 2)
    Includes illustrations
  - "Silly Sagas of the Sea," drafts, undated (Box 2)
  - "Songs of Sorts," drafts, 1937, undated (Box 2)
  - "Spring," draft, 1927 (Box 2)
  - Unsorted manuscript material, undated (Box 2)
  - "Danford Barney: Poet" by Francis H. Bangs, draft and printed version, 1953, undated (Box 2)
- Photographs, undated; Series III; (3 folders)
  Series III. Photographs contains photographic prints made by Barney of various people and places.
  - Negatives, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
- Other Material, 1896-1950; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series IV. Other Material contains identification papers, including a birth certificate and passport, biographical and genealogical material in family papers, and clippings and printed ephemera relating to Barney.
  - Certificate of Birth (copy), 1927 May 25 (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 1931-1947 (Box 2)
  - "Comments + Reviews of DNB as Poet", 1942-1945, undated (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence and clippings
  - Empty envelope, undated (Box 2)
  - Family papers, 1896, undated (Box 2)
  - Passport, 1950 May 11 (Box 2)
  - Printed ephemera, [circa 1929-1947]; 4 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1917-1919 (Box 3)
- Oversize, 1950, undated; 1.46 linear feet (5 boxes)
  - Photographs (In Series III), undated (Box 4 (Oversize))
  - Photographs (In Series III), undated (Box 5 (Oversize))
  - Photographs (In Series III), undated (Box 6 (Oversize))
  - Photographs (In Series III), undated (Box 7 (Oversize))
  - Photographs (In Series III), undated (Box 8 (Oversize))
- Cold Storage, undated; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Nitrate negatives (In Series III), undated (Box 9 (cold storage))
    Conditions Governing Access
    Box 9 (nitrate negatives): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.